Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Why don't you come inside?
Do you think I'm going to eat you?
I dare not.
You look as if we have become enemies.
May I ask what Your Highness calls me for?
There's a suspicion in my mind.
I hope taking my pulse will bring some clarity.
Yes.
My Lady ...
It seems
my dream came true.
Is it...
is it from that night?
Don't bother telling me this is a crime
that will get my whole clan executed.
This is my child.
I'll protect him with my life;
I'll ensure he has a peaceful life.
Shichu, please help me.
Do not let this dream turn into a nightmare.
Is this the time when His Majesty comes back from the court?
Yes, I have confirmed it.
Then look hard for it.
What are you looking for here so early?
Peace to Your Majesty.
I lost a bracelet.
I wouldn't care so much, but
Your Majesty granted it to me my first year in the palace.
I cherish it dearly.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Help find the bracelet.
Aye.
You don't dress in bright colors often.
You look graceful and endearing in this dress.
The dress is honored to gain Your Majesty's compliment.
Your Majesty, we found the bracelet.
Don't be concerned if you lose it again.
There are plenty in the storehouse.
No replacement would have the affection I hold for this one.
Your Majesty's favorite tea has been prepared at the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Will Your Majesty come?
How can I decline since you have prepared it?
Did the sun ... come out from the west today?
"Little rabbits," follow!
You're here.
Find a chair.
Lunar, go cut some fruit.
Yes.
You've been living with great modesty these years.
This dress was made the year I left.
I picked out some fine fabrics for you,
to make new dresses.
You are sending me everything.
You've only been back for a few months,
but my palace is going to overflow from your gifts.
Yes, but now you are all stocked up.
Your Highness Consort Lumière is also here.
Peace to Consort Lumière.
Peace to Concubine Vertu.
Your Highness,
these are gifts from His Majesty.
Please accept them.
Lunar, take them.
Mr. Su, thank you for coming here.
Please take these to buy some tea.
I'm unworthy.
These are too valuable.
I thank Your Highness.
His Majesty said these gifts are meant to ease your boredom, Your Highness.
Please also get prepared, Your Highness.
The Phoenix Carriage will be here to pick you up tonight.
Please thank His Majesty for me.
Allow me to take my leave.
Congratulations.
Is it your luck changing,
or is it your temper?
It's neither good nor bad,
nor related to luck or temper.
One has to keep living.
Life ... has to move forward.
Su Peisheng.
Yes.
Consort Lumière is pregnant. Serve her the plum soup.
Your Majesty, I had the plum soup ready in advance.
Your Majesty,
the plum soup looks appetizing.
Please ask Consort Lumière for a serving for me.
I know you can drink.
Su Peisheng, fill up Concubine Vertu's wine cup.
Aye.
Your Majesty,
I'm pregnant,
so I should avoid drinking.
Since when?
How many months has it been?
I felt unwell yesterday,
so I called in Dr. Wen.
He told me I've been pregnant for two months.
Very well.
Indeed it should be two months.
Congratulations, Concubine Vertu.
Since Concubine Vertu is pregnant,
- Su Peisheng.
- Yes.
Change Concubine Vertu's dishes to be the same as Consort Lumière's.
Yes.
This summer,
the chrysanthemums in the harem bloomed much earlier.
I was worried that it was an ill omen.
Now it seems it was auspicious.
Huan Huan and Meizhuang are both pregnant.
There has never been such a joyful time in the harem.
Now you have become the most precious.
The Empress Dowager sends health tonics every day.
And the Empress sends Autumn over three times a day.
It's annoying to see Autumn here.
I have to fake a smile despite knowing she's up to no good.
It's exhausting.
Indeed.
The Empress has been sick for months.
Meanwhile, two high-ranking concubines got pregnant.
Of course she is anxious.
This time, even if she has "three heads and six arms,"
she can't handle it all.
Just save yourself from any mental labor.
Remember to have a light diet.
Don't drink too much tea or eat too much spicy food.
Keep away from any incense.
Your belly becomes bigger and
your words become more maternal.
I've been getting an earful of these words,
and my ears are almost growing calluses.
My good intention is wasted, it seems.
I'm glad the Empress Dowager sent
Wen Shichu to take care of your pregnancy.
I don't trust anyone else.
If Her Majesty sent someone else,
I wouldn't accept them.
He has been taking care of my health all these years.
I won't believe a word from any other imperial doctors.
You have been pregnant for almost eight months.
I'm pregnant for less than three months.
It's the most unstable time for pregnancy.
He must be exhausted looking after us both.
This is hard work for him.
As long as you and your child are safe and healthy,
his effort over these years will be recognized.
Right.
This child came unexpectedly,
but I will do everything to protect it.
Even though you don't forgive His Majesty,
the child is innocent, after all.
The emperor is the emperor, and my child is my child.
They cannot be mentioned on equal terms.
Meizhuang, don't lie in bed all day.
Let's go visit Consort Honnête with Consort Estime.
Sure.
Concubine Vertu got pregnant after many years in the harem.
Your good fortune makes me feel that
even I have a life to look forward to.
I deserve punishment for being careless.
Peace to Your Highnesses.
Is His Majesty inside?
Yes.
His Majesty is visiting Consort Honnête.
How coincidental. We'll take our leave then.
Mr. Su,
having served His Majesty for so many years,
you deserve some rest now and then.
Otherwise, how would you have energy for all your tasks?
I thank Your Highness.
Sir, you dropped something.
Oh my.
Look at this.
How beautifully done!
It reminds me of Concubine Aide,
who was best at weaving tassel knots.
But her knots aren't as fine as this one.
It seems to resemble your work.
Your Highness speaks too highly of me. I...
Take good care of it.
Thank you, Your Highness.
My Lady, Concubine An is here.
I hope my late-night visit doesn't disturb you, Meizhuang.
What brings you here, Lingrong?
I came specifically to congratulate you on your pregnancy.
I hope you don't mind that I invited myself.
Not at all. You've come at a good time.
I want to make a tiger-head hat for my child
to keep him warm as soon as he is born.
But I can't embroider the whiskers right.
Let me see.
How about this?
It looks very different now with your skilled hands.
It will look nicer if you add pearls onto the whiskers.
I like that idea. Teach me more, please.
My Lady, please have the prenatal tonic.
It's bad for your eyes to do needlework
for too long during pregnancy.
Thank you very much, Dr. Wen.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your appetite is even worse than Consort Lumière's.
Are you not eating well these days?
You look unwell today.
My lady started to feel sick late last night,
and couldn't sleep well.
What was wrong? Have you called for a doctor?
The doctor said I'm fine.
But you look really unwell.
It might be because I got tired from
talking to Lingrong last night.
I couldn't fall asleep after that.
Concubine An was here?
I thought she was in isolation.
Lingrong rarely comes, so I didn't want to turn her away.
After all, we are like sisters.
But My Lady ... You get unwell every time you see Concubine An.
Is that true?
I dare not lie to Your Majesty.
I know.
Tell Su Peisheng
to inform Concubine An
to stop coming to the Palace of Pearl Jade.
I don't want her to bring bad luck to Concubine Vertu.
Yes.
Have some porridge.
Yes. I thank Your Majesty.
How do you read this character?
Da.
[大 large]
Longyue is so smart.
How about adding a dot under "da"?
Tai.
[太 overly]
Very good, my Longyue.
Your Highness, the Fourth Prince is here.
Show him in.
Peace to Your Highness Consort Estime.
Gege.
[elder brother]
What brings you here so early, Hongli?
I was passing by on my way to pay respects to Mother.
I hoped to pick up Longyue so she can come with me.
Fourth Prince, you are very well-mannered.
You come here to bring the Princess to the
Palace of Eternal Longevity every other day.
Longyue is the daughter of Mother.
It's only right for us to fulfill our filial duties to Mother.
Exactly. Go now so you can return early.
May I bring Longyue back after having breakfast
in the Palace of Eternal Longevity?
Certainly.
You two go with the princess.
Yes.
I'll take my leave, Your Highness.
Ruyi,
do you think Consort Lumière
told the Fourth Prince to do this?
Is she ...
really going to take Longyue away from me?
Don't overthink, Your Highness.
Your Majesty, Consort Estime came with me.
Bring her in.
Yes.
How is the Empress's illness?
Her Majesty has had a severe migraine for several days.
She's about to recover.
I'm afraid that after she recovers,
I'll have endless headaches.
Everyone thinks I've been pregnant for only eight months.
We need to have preparations for every circumstance.
Don't worry, Your Highness.
Everything is ready.
My due date is near.
But Concubine Vertu's pregnancy is in the
first three months and not yet stable.
I entrust you with the safety of Concubine Vertu and her child.
What's wrong?
You look haggard these days.
My mind was wandering.
Nothing serious.
Now you are responsible for looking after
Concubine Vertu and me, and our children.
You must be exhausted.
But how can you take care of us
if you don't look after yourself?
I used to think that as a doctor,
I could cure people and save lives.
But ...
that's not the fact.
What makes you speak such discouraged words?
I'm not feeling discouraged.
But the longer I stay in the palace,
the more things are out of my control.
Everyone feels constrained.
Everyone has their difficulties.
Whatever happens, happens.
Just move forward, step by step.
But there are some things -
that I never thought would happen to me.
Does that matter?
A man has to face up to his own responsibilities.
No matter what you encounter, don't bow down to it.
Not only for yourself,
but also for others.
A man's responsibilities...
Your Highness.
No, Huan'er.
If I had made the biggest mistake...
would you forgive me?
Any mistakes you might have made -
I am not the one to forgive them.
As long as your heart has no regrets.
Otherwise, try your best to make up for it.
And don't repeat the same mistake.
You are exactly right, Huan'er.
I will do my best to
take care of Concubine Vertu.
Even if I have to "walk through fire and boiling water."
Allow me to take my leave.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Follow us to get updates on the translation progress.
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
My Lady, why are you in a daze?
The Household Department brought two boxes of tributary tangerines.
I accepted them.
Jinxi loves those tangerines, remember to save some for her.
Where is Jinxi?
You know where she would be
other than in our palace.
Keep those words inside your heart.
Don't speak them out loud.
Her Majesty the Empress.
Her Highness Consort Honnête.
Her Highness Consort Estime.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Consort Lumière, usually I would not
come to your palace.
I am here only because you are the birth mother of Princess Longyue,
and pregnant.
To protect your prestige in this issue,
I have had to ask both Consort Honnête and Consort Estime
to come here with me.
I thank Your Majesty for the caring words.
I do not know what has happened.
Would Your Majesty please be explicit?
I have been sick for months
and have had no strength to resolve anything
even if I had the heart to.
So I left every single thing
under Consort Honnête and Consort Estime's care.
Consort Honnête's health has always been weak.
Consort Estime needs to look after Princess Longyue.
so she already has a lot to take care of.
It's natural that they have overlooked some issues.
May Your Majesty's anger be calmed, the negligence is mine.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
The peace in the harem has great relation to stability in the imperial court.
So I have to be excessively careful.
But now today,
this kind of issue happened right under our noses.
And in your palace.
That is why I am so shocked and angry.
Please enlighten me.
In the palace of the Ming Dynasty,
many maids and eunuchs had intimate relationships
and became "eat-together partners."
Gradually they developed into factions and interfered in state governance.
Half the reason for the Ming Dynasty's ruin was due to this.
So, the palace rules in our dynasty are strict.
Although we have rarely heard of any occurrence of "eat-together partnerships,"
we found one today
right under our eyes!
Autumn.
Consort Lumière, do you recognize this?
It looks very familiar.
I seem to have seen it before somewhere.
This tassel knot resembles the word of my maid Jinxi.
Well-spotted. It is exactly from Cui Jinxi.
Jinxi must have been very careless.
She still cannot look after her belongings at this age.
I thank Your Majesty.
I’ll discipline her when she comes back.
Losing an item is nothing serious.
The issue is that
this item had been kept closely by Su Peisheng.
Cui Jinxi has already been detained.
You don’t need to instruct her anymore.
Consort Estime.
Go ahead.
Y... Yes.
A few days ago, Consort Lumière, Concubine Vertu
and I went to visit Consort Honnête.
We happened to come across Su Peisheng.
When... he was bowing to us,
this item dropped from his sleeve.
The belongings of a maid mustn’t be kept closely by a eunuch.
Just a knot can’t indicate anything.
Perhaps Jinxi lost this item
and Su Peisheng happened to have picked it up.
Perhaps he was planning to return it to her.
A tassel knot is not enough evidence.
But what do the coupling willow leaves mean?
Consort Lumière, you should know that.
As the clue has emerged,
I can’t pretend to not have noticed.
While we’re all here today, it’s necessary to search Cui Jinxi’s room -
to investigate thoroughly, and also to avoid material for gossip.
Jinxi is my personal maid.
Your Majesty need not exert yourself.
Please allow me instead.
How can you do such things carrying a baby?
Furthermore, you’d better avert suspicion.
Spring, Autumn.
Examine Cui Jinxi’s room.
Don’t miss a single thing.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Consort Lumière, you’re pregnant.
Have a seat.
Let’s wait and see what they can find.
Search carefully. Don’t miss any corners!
Yes.
Madam Autumn.
Such filth defiling the harem!
You should all take a look.
They are both senior servants in the palace.
How could they have done such a thing?
To prevent their juniors from following the example,
I can’t leave them unpunished.
I boldly entreat a favor from Your Majesty.
Jinxi is my close servant.
May Your Majesty entrust her punishment to me?
Your servants belong to the harem.
I can't remain uninvolved in any affair within the harem.
The palace servants must always show discretion.
“Observe Heaven's laws and eliminate human desires.”
That's how they can devote themselves to their masters.
Otherwise, how much trouble would arise?
Consort Lumière, you’d better think of the greater good.
Your Majesty represents virtue in the eyes of
the Empress Dowager and His Majesty
and is admired by all in the harem.
I believe Your Majesty will uphold justice
to protect the royal prestige while restoring discipline in the palace.
I certainly will.
I am the master of the harem.
I must administer justice and bring peace to everyone.
Consort Lumière, you just mind your pregnancy.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
The empress has finally made a move.
My Lady, aren't you afraid?
Afraid?
If I'm afraid and let her drag Jinxi down,
the next one will be you.
And then, myself.
No one would escape.
Now that Jinxi is detained,
if this matter escalates, what shall we do?
If gossip spreads,
not only will it cast a shadow on Jinxi's life,
but also your reputation, My Lady...
At this point, does my reputation matter
more than Jinxi's life?
Whatever it takes - I must save Jinxi.
Your Majesty, Consort Lumière is here.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
No bowing, sit.
It's not as if this is your first day following your shifu.
How can you be so careless on your own?
I drink my tea hot.
This is already cold and I can hardly smell the aroma.
My offense deserves death.
Your Majesty, Xiao-Xiazi is very young.
Please don't get angry with him.
He'll get better over time.
Xiao-Xiazi, bring another pot of hot water.
Yes.
Su Peisheng is not here.
All these people stopped behaving themselves.
They cannot do a single thing well.
A herd of good horses need to be led by
an old one to walk steadily and smoothly.
Even more so these servants,
who are used to taking orders.
Now that Su Peisheng is detained,
no wonder they're like "headless flies."
The Empress has spoken with me
about Su Peisheng and Cui Jinxi.
I was worried you might be upset,
so I was planning to visit you after reviewing these memorandums.
You brought yourself here already.
It's my fault that
I didn't discipline my servants well.
If what you say is the case --
Su Peisheng started to serve me when I was young,
doesn't that mean I also cannot discipline the servants?
They did what they did.
There was nothing we could have done about it.
After what has happened,
my heart has been unsettled, as if hanging in the air.
Even though Jinxi made a mistake,
she has served me for so many years after all.
I'm angry but worried about her at the same time.
You're with child now.
You need to give priority to your pregnancy.
The Empress's health is getting better.
She can attend to the harem affairs now.
Besides,
if you're upset about losing Cui Jinxi,
I'll ask the Household Department to send you someone better.
My Lady, why didn't you plead with His Majesty?
Only His Majesty can command the Empress now.
The Empress came well prepared and got solid evidence.
With the harem rules in place, His Majesty cannot say much.
If I begged His Majesty, I'd be inviting myself
into the Empress's "burning charcoal urn."
She'd find me guilty for conniving and indulgence.
What do we do then?
If you're implicated, My Lady,
there's no one else that can save Jinxi.
Let's go to the Department of Penalty.
It's very stuffy and hot there.
How can Your Highness go there while you're pregnant?
Your Highness should avoid it.
I've even been to the Cold Palace - so many times.
What's there to be afraid of in the Department of Penalty?
It's already tiring for Your Ladyship carrying the baby.
Even if you aren't concerned for yourself,
you should protect the little prince
from the vile qi of the Department of Penalty.
If he cannot overcome this little hardship,
how can he be my child?
Let's go.
Do your work, don't get lazy!
It's not a place for you slack off!
What are you doing?!
It's warm here.
Why do they use such thick quilts?
It's one punishment in the Department of Penalty
to use the quilts and hay here.
It's unbearably hot already;
sleeping here easily gives people heat rash.
But when it's ice-cold in winter,
only thin blankets are provided.
Some have frozen to death.
Jinxi is probably pounding rice as her punishment.
Detainers in the Department of Penalty
can only sleep four hours per day,
and have to pound rice non-stop all the time.
Do your work, don't be lazy!
What are you doing? Move faster!
Work, lazybones!
Don't you dare slack off again!
Faster!
Do you still want to live?!
Do it better!
Bitch, work harder!
What are you looking at?
Work faster, lazybones!
Still slacking? You wanna die?!
I'm talking to you!
I didn't know Your Highness Consort Lumière was coming.
I bid peace to Your Highness.
Is someone named Cui Jinxi here?
Yes yes, she just got here.
She's pounding rice over there.
Madam, is it convenient
for me to have a few words with her?
Yes yes.
Please wait here, I'll call her over.
Cui Jinxi, come here!
Your Highness, please take your time.
I'll just be watching others over there.
Thank you.
Why are you all here?
(So slow, faster!)
How could Your Highness come here while pregnant?
(I'll beat you to death. What are you doing?)
It's my fault to have implicated Your Highness...
and made you come to this foul place.
I suppose... many are
laughing at Your Highness outside.
I'm so ashamed ... I don't deserve to see Your Highness again.
If you had implicated me,
how could I have come here to see you?
Back then, you did this wholeheartedly for me,
and now you have ended up here...
I owe it to you.
Don't worry.
I will find a way to get you out of here.
No no, Your Highness is pregnant.
You must not exert your mind.
It could affect the prenatal qi.
I knew from the beginning
that if this was found out,
it wouldn't end well.
Not to mention that...
this has been firmly grasped by the Empress.
Also,
even if Your Highness tried very hard to save me,
I'd be too ashamed to
keep living in the palace.
It's better to just let my life take its course here...
Jinxi.
Your Highness.
it was really difficult to return to the palace.
You need to consider the big picture.
It's all right to sacrifice me.
Protect yourself
and give birth to the child safely.
Then I'd die with no regret.
Death is the easiest way out.
Just hang oneself and then it's over.
But if you did that, it would "sadden the allies
and gladden the enemies."
It's not worth it.
Given our relationship all these years,
trust me,
I'll get you out of here.
But Your Highness,
please don't come to this foul place again.
I will take good care of myself.
Do you know where Su Peisheng is now?
I suppose the same as me,
he's being punished somewhere.
I dragged him down...
Otherwise,
he'd still be the palace's head eunuch.
I didn't have much expectation
about Su Peisheng.
Just that the two of us...
could have each other to rely on for the rest of our lives.
But the other day, at the Department of Penalty,
he didn't inform against me despite all the torture.
That gave me ... some true feelings for him.
"Misfortune reveals the true heart."
It's truly rare.
Back then, looking at you and him...
I thought you were the ideal couple,
"a talented man and a beautiful woman."
Now that I have experienced the feelings myself,
I finally understand how "Misfortune reveals the true heart."
Don't worry.
I'll make sure he is taken care of as well.
You must take care of yourself.
I'm fine.
Her Highness Consort Lumière.
Honnête.
Lumière.
I see that you're reading.
I hope this isn't a bad time?
After what happened in your palace,
I suppose you're not here
to chit-chat with me.
I'm eager to see you, Honnête.
I wonder if you're willing to help me.
Tell me what you're thinking. Have a seat.
My mind is set on saving Jinxi and Su Peisheng.
Of course, it's also for His Majesty.
Su Peisheng has served His Majesty for many years.
He knows His Majesty's temper and habits the best.
Now he's suddenly detained.
First, it damages the prestige of His Majesty;
second, no one else can serve His Majesty as attentively,
causing His Majesty uneasiness all day.
You're right.
Noble Lady Délice, please stop.
Her Majesty the Empress.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty has finally come.
I feel so aggrieved being locked up here.
It does look much worse than the Palace of Gathering Excellence.
Your Majesty, I'm being confined here,
and have no idea when I can get out.
Has His Majesty already forgotten about me?
Do you want to get out so badly?
Your Majesty, please save me.
Soon it will be the Mid-Autumn Festival.
I'll suggest to His Majesty to end your confinement.
You should know
how to return my favor.
I'll obey Your Majesty's bidding at all cost.
Even if it's not for Your Majesty,
I remember for my own sake who framed me.
His Majesty the Emperor.
His Majesty is here.
I greet Your Majesty.
Rise, rise.
You look better today.
I thank Your Majesty.
You've always been weak.
You should be careful about your health.
[Mencius]
What interest do you have in reading this?
The teachings of Confucius and Mencius are profound.
I enjoy them a lot.
You like Mencius.
What's your opinion about his ideas?
Compared with Mencius,
Zhu Xi seems quite shallow.
[A Confucian scholar in Song Dynasty]
Yet Zhu Xi called himself a Fuzi
[great scholar].
Although his studies were renowned as part of the Cheng-Zhu school,
he completely misinterpreted the philosophy of Confucius and Mencius.
How so?
Mencius said that "male and female dwelling together
is the greatest of human relations."
But Zhu Xi proposed:
“Observe Heaven's laws and eliminate human desires.”
It doesn't flow from Mencius's belief.
Zhu Xi does seem to lack empathy there.
It's also the case in the palace.
If we follow Zhu Fuzi's proposition,
how could the concubines bring
heirs to Your Majesty?
Therefore, I think whoever says something like this
must be a heartless person.
It runs counter to the benevolence of the imperial family.
The benevolence...
Have you seen someone recently?
Did you hear something?
Your Majesty, I'm constantly unwell
and only stay in my place.
Even if I do go out,
Your Majesty knows that
I'm the person least likely to meddle with the affairs of others,
or gossip about them.
That's true.
It's your best merit in my view.
If so, I'd like to ask your opinion on one thing.
Yes.
Currently, the harem is gossiping about
the affair between Cui Jinxi and Su Peisheng.
The Empress advises harsh punishment.
Consort Estime withdrew her opinion.
It's not fitting for Consort Lumière to speak.
What do you think?
The beauties in the palace are like flowers.
Nobody can say which flower is the best.
Take the peach blossom as an example.
People who like it say it "brings harmony to a family."
Those who dislike it "discard them to flow away with the river."
Yet all eyes have seen the same flower.
And right or wrong are determined by the human heart.
Regarding this affair,
the Empress thinks it's related to
the rules and discipline in the palace;
I beg to differ.
They didn't cause any disorder in the harem.
It's just a maid and a eunuch
finding consolation in each other.
The servants, once sent to the palace, work hard until their death.
It's inevitable they feel lonely and sorrowful.
They just want to find a companion.
I'd feel pitiful if I were in their shoes.
How do you think we should resolve this issue then?
Your Majesty, have you heard this saying:
"You can't be the man of the house
if you don't have a deaf ear and a blind eye".
It's an "eat-together relationship" between a maid and a eunuch.
If every palace
is thoroughly investigated,
I imagine Your Majesty can easily find
many other “eat-together partners."
Should they all be executed?
Your Majesty is the Emperor of the country and the ruler under Heaven.
You bear much more serious responsibilities than "the man of the house."
Why not be more tolerant
and "turn big problems into small ones,
and small problems into no problems at all"?
Perhaps it's because I see Consort Lumière and Concubine Vertu
are both pregnant,
They cannot bear to hear the sounds of beatings and killing.
Yes.
We have some pregnant concubines now.
I suppose they cannot bear to see any killings.
All right, you should rest well.
I'm going back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
One more thing, Your Majesty.
It's getting cold. Please ask your servants
to add some chrysanthemums to your tea.
I see the corners of the lips are peeling.
I will.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.